New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice; Records apap012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice Records
1971-1986
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice
apap012
19.25 cubic ft.
Formed in reaction to the Rockefeller Administration's crack-down following the Attica Prison riot, the New York State Coalition For Criminal Justice's primary mission was to reform what it regarded as an excessively harsh criminal justice system in New York.
Biographical Sketch
The New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice, Center for Justice Education, Inc. was founded in 1974 in Rochester, New York as the New York State Committee for Criminal Justice. It adopted the name New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice later in 1974. In the early 1970s a number of Rochester community leaders became concerned about "the effectiveness and fairness of local criminal justice operations", specifically focusing their concerns on police brutality, court procedures, and jail conditions. They formed the Task Force on the Courts under the leadership of Church Women United. In early 1972, Rochester's Judicial Process Commission (RJPC), lead by Virginia Mackey and Carolyn Micklem, was created under the auspices of the Genesee Ecumenical Ministry. The RJPC won considerable state and national recognition for its work.
Following the suppression of the Attica prison uprising in 1971, the Judicial Process Commission (JPC) initiated a state wide assessment of the underlying causes of the Attica tragedy. The JPC established ties with the lobbyists of statewide organizations such as the Urban Coalition, Community Service Society, the Citizen's Union, the New York State Council of Churches, and other groups forming the New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice. The Coalition's mission was to increase New York State citizens' knowledge and understanding of the laws, structure, policies and practices of the criminal justice system. In addition, the Coalition advocated alternative correctional policy choices, and devised and coordinated strategies to improve the quality of criminal justice in New York State. The Coalition for Criminal Justice formed the Rapid Communication Network in 1975, to inform and mobilize public opinion on issues related to criminal justice. The RCN relays weekly information from Albany to satellite networks spread across the state. The chair person of the coalition was also the head of the network, and held satellite training conferences for the various coordinators and policy committee members.
The New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice is governed by a Board of Directors, who determines the nature and content of the coalition's programs. Board Members are appointed by incorporators, on a two year basis and members may be reelected for a succeeding two years. The board passes motions by majority vote, and consists of no fewer than seven members, but no more than nine. The board appoints a President, Vice-President, and Secretary-Treasurer who serve one term and carry out the work of the coalition. The Board of Directors may also form committees when necessary. Day to day operations are carried out by a paid director, first appointed in 1976. The first paid director of the coalition was Irene Jackson. There are two yearly meetings of the board, and one of the membership.
The programs and policies of the organization are established by the Board of Directors. There are three classes of directors, elected by all voting members, directors elected by caucuses, and directors selected by sustaining organizational members. In all, the Board includes twenty-five members with one year terms. Officers of the Board of Directors included chairperson (president), vice chairperson (vice president), director (chief administrator), secretary, and treasurer. The chairperson of the board appoints the chairs of committees. Several committees were created including, the nominations committee, membership, finance and fund raising, legislative, personnel, executive, and the policy committee which was the most important committee.
Membership by application is open to all individuals and organizations with a proven interest in supporting the principles of the organization, and who pay the dues set by the Board of Directors. ["Background History the New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice"]. The organization has four classes of membership, individual membership, supporting organization membership, which includes any organization providing significant financial support, organizational membership, which includes any organization supporting the reform of the criminal justice system, and last, an associate member, that is someone whose membership may cause a conflict of interest. All members had one vote, except the associate members who had none. The initial location of the organization was 362 State Street, but in 1978 it moved to the First Presbyterian Church within walking distance of the capitol.
Prominent organizational leaders included the first Chair Person/Director & Coordinator Irene Jackson 1976-82, Administrative Assistant/Assistant Director (1978-82) and Interim Director (1982-83) Diane Geary, Director Richard V. Avant, 1983, and Executive Director Van Zwisohn, 1984-, Policy Committee Chairs Camille Smith (1978-79) and Douglas McDonald (1979-80), and Good-Time Project Coordinator (1981-82) Planning and Legislative Coordinator (1982-83) and Assistant Director (1983) Peter Pollack.
Funding of the organization was provided through membership fees, gifts from member organizations, and a grant from the New York Council of Churches.
Scope and Contents
Formed in reaction to the Rockefeller Administration's crack-down following the Attica Prison riot, the New York State Coalition For Criminal Justice primary mission was to reform what it regarded as an excessively harsh criminal justice system in New York. It carried out that mission by lobbying the New York State Legislature and the State departments involved in the criminal justice system. The Coalition sought to bring public pressure for change to bear on the Legislature and State departments by forming (January 1975) a Rapid Communication Network as a mechanism to develop a state wide letter writing campaign. Among the records of the Coalition is documentation relating to Coalition's involvement in major issues of criminal justice reform such as the reach of the criminal law, length of sentences set by the legislature, court functions including bail and preventive detention issues, jails, prisons, probation, parole (see the Good Time Survey and initiative of 1981), ex-offenders services, victims, and families of offenders. While the a few items in the records date from the early seventies and also cover the period 1985-1986, the overwhelming bulk of the records cover the period 1975-1884.
The Coalition was hostile to Governor Cuomo attempts to expand the prison system in New York and consequently there is considerable documentation relating to the Coalition's 1981 campaign to block the Prison Bond Issue. There is also considerable documentation of the Coalition's 1970s and 1980s campaign against the reinstitution of the death penalty in New York between 1979 and 1984. Initially, the Coalition sought reform by lobbying the New York State Legislature. Following a flurry of legislative criminal justice reform activity in 1975 and 1976, that forum for positive change narrowed considerably and it became clear that although legislative reform would always be a key Coalition goal, the Coalition needed to change its focus and work to reform the administration of justice by focusing its energies on New York State agencies as Department of Corrections and the Division of Parole. There is considerable documentation regarding the Coalitions involvement with those agencies.
The broad interest of the Coalition can be seen in its monthly newsletter, Updates and in the Annual Meetings of the Coalition as well as the Director's Administrative files. Contained in the records are the original survey forms and the data compiled as a result of the 1981 "Good Time Survey" of prison staff and inmate attitudes toward the granting of early release or parole to inmates for good behavior. There is also information on programs established as alternatives to incarceration in 1975-80. The Coalition's monitoring of proposed bills relating to criminal justice and lobbied for changes in the wording of the bills is fully documented in the records. Among the bills found in the legislative files are bill jackets with suggestions for changes in language relating to criminal procedure laws, correctional law, and the penal law.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Coalition Administration Files, 1975-1984
Series 2: Coalition Meetings File, 1975-1983
Series 3: Funding Files, 1976-1982
Series 4: New York State Commission of Corrections, 1975-1983
Series 5: Correctional Facilities File, 1975-1981
Series 6: Division of Parole File, 1973-1983
Series 7: Department of Correctional Services Files, 1972-1983
Series 8: "Good-Time" Attitude Survey, 1981
Series 9: Issues File, 1971-1984
Series 10: Legislation File, 1963-1986
Series 11: Publications File, 1976-1985
Series arrangement statement: SUNY will complete.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of series 5.
Criminal Justice and Prisons; Prisons -- New York (State); Prison reformers -- New York (State); Prisoners -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Criminal justice, Administration of -- New York (State); Capital punishment -- New York (State); New York State Coalition for Criminal Justice.; New York State Committee for Criminal Justice.
- Coalition Administration Files, 1975-1984; 1; 5.33 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  The series is the main correspondence/subject file of the CCJ. It contains the correspondence, 1976-1982, predominantly of CCJ Chair/Director & Coordinator Irene Jackson, 1976-1982. To a lesser degree of Diane Geary, CCJ Administrative Assistant/Assistant Director 1979-1982, and Interim Director 1982-1983; Director Richard V. Avant, 1983; Executive Director Van Zwishohn, 1984; Good Time Project coordinator, 1981-1982, Planning and Legislative Coordinator 1982-1983, and Assistant Director Peter Pollack, 1982-1983; his successor as legislative coordinator Sandra Mitchell, 1983-1984, mostly with the New York State Commission of Corrections. Also includes correspondence with Senator Marino, Coalition members, the Department of Correctional Services, the Monroe County Legal Assistance Corporation (Greater Upstate Law Project), the Medical Society N.Y. State, the Council of Churches, the Creative Communications Committee of Green Haven, Prison Families Anonymous, INC., the Prison Outreach and Prevention Program, the Osborne Association, INC., the John Jay College of Criminal Justice, the Volunteer Attorney Service Teams for N.Y. State Prisons, Amnesty International, Prison Research Education Actions Project, Westchester Alliance, Prisoner's Accelerated Creative Exposure, INC., Prisoner Rehabilitation, INC., Full Step, INC., and the Fortune Society. The correspondence documents the mission of the organization, which is reforming the state's criminal justice system by educating citizens about the law. To improve the quality of the system, the CCJ advocates alternatives to the traditional criminal justice policy of incarceration. These alternatives include bail reform, sentencing reform, good time reform, second felony offender laws, redirecting correctional resources from prisons to community programs, expansion of the state temporary release program, victim restitution programs, community dispute resolution programs, and fighting against the death penalty and prison expansion. Other materials include: a December 29, 1981 draft article by Irene Jackson on the history, personnel & responsibilities, and programs of the Coalition financial/budget records, legal grants manuals, Good-Time reform project information, membership lists 1979-1980/82, prisoners legal services of N.Y. employee list 1981, judicial process committee membership list 1980, minority business directory, and lists of alternative programs. Series also contains photographs from supersession, training weekend, and Coalition staff. Cassette tapes contain audio from Community Correction Conference.
  - Access, Disabled Persons Access To Churches, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Alternatives To Incarceration, 1975-1982 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Amnesty International, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Anchor Association, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Attica Clemency Legislation, Undated (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Benjamin v. Malcolm, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Bureau of Records, Distribution of Inmates in New York State Prisons, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - Carey, Hugh, Press Releases on Clemency and other Bills, 1976-1981 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - Christians United In Mission, Inc., 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 10)
  - Citizens Committee On Prison Overcrowding, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 11)
  - CCJ Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - CCJ Budget & finance, 1976-1980 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - CCJ Constitution, By-Laws, Guidelines, & History, 1980-1984 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - CCJ Director's reports, 1977-1982 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - CCJ Filing System, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - CCJ Finance - Cash reserve reports, 1981 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - CCJ Finance - Cash reserve reports, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - CCJ Finances: New York State Council of Churches, Undated (Box 2 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - CCJ Financial reports, 1978-1986 (Box 3 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - CCJ Meetings, Minutes, and Membership, 1976-1979 (Box 3 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - CCJ Policy Committee Meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 3 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - CCJ Policy Committee Members, 1976-1980 (Box 3 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - CCJ policy recommendations, 1976-1979; 1980 (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - CCJ Survey Questionnaire, 1982 (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - CCJ Supersession photographs, 1979-1980; 5 folders (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - CCJ Training weekend photographs, 1979; 2 folders (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Computer run, 1981-1982 (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Conferences attended (folder 1), 1978-1979; 1980-1981 (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Conferences attended (folder 2), 1980-1981 (Box 4 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Conferences attended (folder 3), 1981-1982 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Correctional Association Of New York, 1979-1982 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Correctional Services News, 1980-1981 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1980-1983 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to Gov. Carey, 1977-1982 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 5 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Coalition staff photographs, 1978-1980 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Crime and Its Victims, 1975 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Cuomo, Mario, 1980-1982 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Death penalty - Resource Organization, 1982-1983 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Death penalty - Contact Lists, 1978; 1980 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Department Of Correctional Services, 1979-1981 (Box 6 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Division of Probation, 1978-1982 (Box 7 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Drinking and Driving, 1980 (Box 7 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Educational Designs for Justice, 1981 (Box 7 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Fortune News, 1980-1981 (Box 7 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Format Samples, 1979; 1980-1982 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Full Step, Inc., 1979-1981 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - "Good-Time" Project, 1979; 1980-1983 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - "Good-Time" Project, 1981-1982 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Go To Jail Task Force, 1978-1979 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Gun Control, 1980 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Hospitality House, 1970-1971 (Box 8 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Institutions, Etc, 1980-1981 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Jails-Overcrowding, Suicides, Classification of Inmates, 1977-1982 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Judicial Process Commission, 1980-1981 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Justicia, 1980-1981 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Life Without Parole, 1980 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Legislative Action Committee Program, 1977-1978; 1980; 1981-1984 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Membership Drive, 1979; 1980-1981 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Membership Dues Mailing List, 1981-1982 (Box 9 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - Minority Business Directory, 1983 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous forms, 1978 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Nassau Coalition For Safety And Justice, 1980-1982 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - National Criminal Justice Reference Service, 1979-1981 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - New Police Corps, 1982 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - National Movement To Boycott Crime, Inc., 1982 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Network Program, 1981-1982 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - NYS Association Of Counties, 1980-1982 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - NYS Catholic Conference, 1981 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - NYS Council Of Churches, 1979-1984 (Box 10 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 10)
  - NYS Council On Children And Families, 1981 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - NYS Criminal Justice Agency, 1980 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - NYS Defenders Association, 1981-1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - NYS Division For Youth, 1981-1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - NYS Freedom Of Information Laws, 1978-1980 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - NYS Higher Education Committee, 1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - NYS Impact Network, 1981 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - NYS Jail Task Force, 1980 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - NYS Prisons, 1981-1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - NYS Probation Officers Association, Inc., 1982-1983 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 10)
  - NYS Assembly Task Force On Crime Victims, 1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 11)
  - NY Women In Criminal Justice Inc., 1982-1983 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 12)
  - Office Expenses, 1978-1979; 1981 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 13)
  - Originals of XEROXED Material, 1979; 1980-1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 14)
  - Personnel: Asst. Director Diane Geary, 1979 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 15)
  - Personnel: Director Irene Jackson, 1977-1979; 1982 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 16)
  - Personnel: Former Employees, 1977-1980 (Box 11 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 17)
  - Personnel: "Good-Time" Project Coordinator Peter Pollack, 1981-1983 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Personnel: Law student intern Christine Germaine, 1979-1980 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Personnel: Legislative Action Coordinator Sandra Mitchell, 1983-1984 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Personnel: Secretary Sarah A. Lawrence, 1982 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Personnel: Student intern Ursula Charleton, 1981-1982 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Personnel: Substitute Secretary Ralene Smith, 1982 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Prison Bond Issues, 1979-1982 (Box 12 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - PREAP, Prison Research Education Action Projects, 1980-1981 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Prisoner Family Project, 1981-1982 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Prisoner Rehabilitation, Inc. PROBE, 1979-1981 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Prisoner's Accelerated Creative Exposure, Inc., 1978-1981 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Prisoner's Legal Services, 1977-1982 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Project Gateway, 1982 (Box 13 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Program information/Jackson speech notes, Group Picture (folder 1), 1976-1979 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Jackson speech notes (folder 2), 1980-1982 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Rochester Interfaith Jail Ministry, 1982 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)
  - Satellite Coordinators, 1980-1981 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 4)
  - Satellite kit for Rapid Communication Network, 1975-1976 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 5)
  - Satellite Legislative Action Day, Albany, 1979 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 6)
  - Satellite membership in Network Areas, 1979 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 7)
  - Satellite reports, 1978-1979 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 8)
  - Satellite Training Conference, 1979 (Box 14 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 9)
  - Satellites - Binghampton Network, 1976-1979 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 1)
  - Satellites - Buffalo Network, 1975-1979 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 2)
  - Satellites - Capital District Network, 1975-1976; 1979-1980 (Box 15 (1-Coalition Administration Files), Folder 3)